黑金企业
1898年
不!
No!
找到了、找到了
There she is. There she is.
找到了
There she is.
“金银成份分析”
“丹尼尔普兰优”
1902年
各位女士先生
Ladies and gentlemen,
我至今已走遍北达克达州大半土地
I've traveled over half our state to be here tonight.
由于新油井的开凿，我来晚了点
I couldn't get away sooner because my new well was coming in
我得去监督一下
at Coyote Hills and I had to see about it.
那口井现在日产两千桶油
That well is now flowing at 2,000 barrels
每周都给我带来五千美元进帐
and it's paying me an income of $5,000 a week.
我还在安特洛有16口量产油井
l have two others drilling and l have 16 producing at Antelope,
各位女士先生，若我说我是油商，你们也会同意
so, ladies and gentlemen,
if l say l'm an oilman, you will agree.
现在，你们有了绝佳的机会
Now, you have a great chance here,
但一不小心还是会赔光本钱
but bear in mind you could lose it all if you're not careful.
在所有凿井碰运气的人之中
Out of all men that beg for a chance to drill your lots,
也许20个有1个能成为油商
maybe one in twenty will be oilmen.
剩下的都是投机客
The rest will be speculators,
所以才有人会介入你们和油商间
that's men trying to get between you and the oilmen
赚取那些原本应属于你们的钱
to get some of the money that ought, by rights, come to you.
就算你们找到的人有钱又想凿井
Even if you find one that has money and means to drill,
他也可能对于凿井一无所知
he'll maybe know nothing about drilling.
那样他就得雇请人手
He'll have to hire the job out on contract,
接着你们就得指望包工
and then you're depending on a contractor,
他的动作俐落纯熟
who'll rush the job through
找新工作就跟他的动作一样快
so he can get another contract just as quick as he can.
这一行就是这样
This is the way that this works.
你出多少？别浪费时间
What is your offer? We're wasting time.
请安静
Please!
我自己凿井
l do my own drilling.
我的手下就是我的手下，他们也是我熟识的人
And the men that work for me,
work for me, and they are men l know.
我认真经营，也谨慎监督
l make it my business to be there and to see their work.
我不会乱扔工具，又到处乱找
l don't lose my tools in the hole
and spend months fishing for them.
我不会敲坏水泥
l don't botch the cementing off
让水流进洞里，搞砸整块地
and let water in the hole and ruin the whole lease.
我是个爱家的人
l'm a family man.
我经营的是家族事业，这是我儿子兼伙伴，H.W.普兰优
l run a family business. This is my son
and my partner, H.W. Plainview.
少有油商能有如此家族伙伴关系
We offer you the bond of family that very few oilmen can understand.
在这一行，只有我是如此做事
l'm fixed like no other company in this field
因为我的灰狼坡油井已开始量产
and that's because my Coyote Hills well has just come in.
我有一组设备随时准备上线
l have a string of tools all ready to put to work.
一周内就能运送整组设备过来
l can load a rig onto trucks and have them here in a week.
钻油井的木头我有熟人会帮忙
l have business connections,
so l can get the lumber for the derricks.
时间这么赶，得靠朋友帮忙
Such things go by friendship in a rush like this.
因此我也敢保证能动手钻探
And this is why l can guarantee to start drilling
并提供现金来证明我说的话
and to put up the cash to back my word.
我向各位保证
l assure you, ladies and gentlemen,
不管其他人保证要怎么做
no matter what the others promise to do,
他们根本做不到我所做的承诺
when it comes to the showdown, they won't be there.
坐下!你没有权利...
Sit down! Sit down, you have no right...
我们讨论一下这人说的话吧
Let us discuss what the man has to say.
- 你相信他吗？- 我们讨论一下吧
-Prescott, do you trust this man?
-Let's discuss what he has to say.
1911年
- 他的话毫无逻辑 - 他知道什么？我的家当都在那里！
-There's logic to what he's saying.
-How does he know? My lot is there!
1911年
- 他的话毫无逻辑 - 他知道什么？我的家当都在那里！
-There's logic to what he's saying.
-How does he know? My lot is there!
两三年，有可能要十年
Two or three years, it could be ten years!
-我们除了互相争执啥都没有 -看看那里的那口井
-We gain nothing by losing our heads!
-Look at that well out there!
没有人在吵架
Nobody's losing their heads.
你不该到这里的
You have no business being here!
叫那女人坐下
Sit that woman down, sir!
你可以坐下
You can sit down.
普兰优先生，请别走
Mr. Plainview! Please, Mr. Plainview.
不，先生，你要去哪里？
No, Mr. Plainview! No, where are you going?
-我不需要租这块地，谢谢 -可是我们需要你
-l don't need the lease. Thank you.
-But we need you.
这太混乱了，谢谢你拨空给我
Too much confusion. Thank you for your time.
不，没有什么混乱
No, no, there's no confusion.
你们心甘情愿，我才会要这块地
l wouldn't take the lease if you gave it to me as a gift.
班克先生，我不想浪费你的时间
Mr. Bankside, I'm not going to waste your time.
我也会感激你不浪费我的时间
I'd certainly appreciate it if you didn't waste mine.
如果你想跟我签约，我们十天内就能开始凿井
Now, if you wish to sign with me, we
can have a well drilling within 10 days.
你的地在现存油井的北边
Your lot is further north from the discovery well up here.
那表示我们可能得凿深一点
That means we'll probably have to dig deeper.
如果那里的油跟我想的一样多
And if there's as much oil here as l think there is,
就会更难凿，不过一凿到就发了
it'll be harder to reach, but once
we find it, we can take it right out.
动作要快，油很快就会被凿光了
We have to act quickly, because
very soon these fields will be dry.
我要你知道自己想怎么做
l need you to know what you want to do.
由于现存油井的距离
Now, because of the distance from the discovery well,
我付的使用费会少一点
l'll pay you a smaller royalty than you'd get down there
不过我会给你一千美元签约金
but l'm prepared to give you a $ 1,000 bonus on your lot.
你说的使用费是多少？
What kind of royalty are you talking about?
六分之一，加上十天内开凿的保证
One-sixth, plus a guarantee to start drilling within 10 days.
这种条件你在别处绝对找不到
Now, that's something you won't find anywhere else.
夫人，你小孩几岁了？
What age are your children, ma'am?
10岁和12岁
Ten and twelve.
普兰优先生，我有个问题，你太太人呢？
Mr. Plainview, a question, sir. Where is your wife?
她因难产过世了，夫人
She died in childbirth, Mrs. Bankside.
我跟儿子一起相依为命
So it's just me and my son now.
就快喷油了，老板
lt's coming in, boss!
听见没？
Hear it?
普兰优先生？
Mr. Plainview?
什么事？
Yes?
你就是丹尼尔普兰优？
Are you Daniel Plainview?
对
Yes.
有何贵干？
What can l do for you?
你在找油
You look for oil.
没错
That's right.
你花多少钱租用有藏油的土地？
What do you pay for a place that has it?
-看情况 -看什么情况？
-Well, that depends. -What does it depend on?
有很多
On a lot of things.
如果我说我知道一个地方有油，那里的地价钱又便宜
lf l told you l knew a place that had oil
where land could be bought cheaply,
你想这消息值多少钱？
what do you think that would be worth?
我想...你该让我知道你知道什么
l think that you should let me know what you know
然后我们再谈交易的事
and then we'll try and work something out.
-我能坐吗？-请坐
-Can l sit down? -Please.
你隶属于哪个教堂？
What church do you belong to?
我...
l...
我不排斥宗教，我没有特别隶属于哪个教堂
l enjoy all faiths. l don't belong
to one church in particular.
我全都爱，全都喜欢。你是从哪来的？
l like them all. l like everything. Where are you from?
那正是我要卖给你的消息
That would be telling you. That's what l want to sell you.
你在西诺丘做什么？
What are you doing in Signal Hill?
我们有油，地上就会渗油
We have oil, and it seeps through the ground.
你想付钱知道地点吗？
Do you want to pay me to know where it is?
地上有油并不代表地下也有
Just 'cause there's something on the ground
doesn't mean there's anything beneath it.
标准石油为什么买上面的地？
Why did Standard Oil buy up land?
这地方在加州？
ls it in California?
-也许吧 -他们买多少地？
-Maybe. -How much land did they buy?
我比较希望你不要把我当笨蛋
l'd like it better if you didn't think l was stupid.
你为什么来找我？
Why did you come to me?
-你才刚挖到油 -没错
-You just brought this well in. -That's right.
所以，现在给我五百元现金
Yes, so just give me $500 in cash right now
我就让你知道地点
and l'll tell you where it is.
这样吧，我现在就给你一百元
l'll tell you what l'll do, son. l'll give you $ 1 00 now,
如果证明那里值得开凿，我就再给你一千元奖金
and if it proves to be a promising lease,
then give you a $ 1,000 bonus.
六百元
Six hundred dollars.
你再告诉我，你们那里有什么
Tell me one thing to help me decide.
What else have you got up there?
你们种什么？
What do you grow?
我们有个大牧场，但大多是石头
We have a big ranch, but it's mostly rocks.
试过种东西，却只长杂草
Plant things. Nothing will grow but weeds.
你以为上面会长什么？
What makes you think it's up?
那里有硫磺吗？还是碱矿？
ls there sulfur around? Or alkali deposits?
附近有碱矿，我不知道硫磺是啥
Alkali nearby. l don't know sulfur.
那是你儿子？
ls that your son?
对
Yes.
- 你好 - 你好
-Hi. -Hi.
-你是谁？-我是费契汉弥顿
-Who are you? -l'm Fletcher Hamilton.
幸会，孩子，你叫什么名字？
Nice to meet you, son. What's your name?
你是做什么的？
What do you do?
我帮普兰优先生做事
l work with Mr. Plainview.
这里有五百元
Here's $500, son.
你告诉我有价值的消息，这钱就是你的了
You tell me something worth hearing, this money's yours.
我来自伊沙贝郡的小波士顿镇
l come from a town called Little Boston in lsabella County.
就是这里。小波士顿有个铁路支线站
This is us, here. Spur station here at Little Boston.
你要找的就是桑德牧场
The Sunday ranch is what you're looking for.
有一条羊肠小径通到那里
There's a sheep trail that takes you there.
由镇上往西走一哩，不远
lt's a mile out of town headed west, not far.
只要走山脚下这条小路
Just through a small pass here near the base of the hills.
你会经过教堂，沿着小径走就行
You'll pass a church and just follow the sheep trail.
-标准石油买下哪里？ -这里和这里
-Where's Standard buying up? -Here and here.
-你姓桑德？ -对
-Your family name is Sunday, yes? -That's right.
你家有多少人？
How many's in your family?
父母、妹妹和我弟弟伊莱
My father and mother and sisters and my brother Eli.
-你有几个妹妹？ -两个
-How many sisters do you have? -Two.
-你叫什么名字？ -保罗
-What's your name? -Paul.
你家人知道石油的存在吗？
Does any of your family know about the oil that you say is there?
我不知道
l don't know.
我叔叔一直说有石油
My uncle always said there was oil there,
但我不知道他们的想法
but l don't know what they heard or what they think.
你们种些什么？
What do you grow?
我们养羊，那是养羊的牧场。我说过，那里只长杂草
lt's goats. lt's a goat farm.
l told you, nothing grows but weeds.
-那里有水吗？ -是咸水
-ls there water? -lt's salty.
只要挖井，出来的几乎都是咸水
You drill a well, it's hard not to get saltwater.
我跟你们说，那里有石油
The oil is there. l'm telling you.
-我想走了 -你可以留下过夜
-l want to go now, so... -You can stay tonight.
-不，我想走了，我要走 -听着，保罗
-No, l want to go now. l want to leave.
-Listen, Paul.
如果我大老远跑去那里，却发现你骗我
lf l travel all the way out there
and l find that you've been lying to me,
我会找到你，拿回加倍的钱
l'm going to find you and l'm going
to take more than my money back.
那样可以吗？
ls that all right with you?
-可以，先生 -那么好吧
-Yes, sir. -All right, then.
-祝你们好运，上帝保佑 -你也是，年轻人
-Nice luck to you. God bless.
-And to you, young man.
有人来了
-There's someone coming. -Thank you, Mary.
-晚安 -晚安
-Good evening. -Good evening.
我叫丹尼尔普兰优，这是我儿子
My name's Daniel Plainview. This is my son, H.W.
-你来打猎的？ -猎鹌鹑
-Are you hunting? -Hunting for quail.
听说桑德牧场附近适合扎营
We're told there might be a good place
to camp up near the Sunday ranch.
这里就是桑德牧场，你可以扎营
This is the Sunday ranch. You can camp here.
-谢谢，你有水吗？ -有的
-Thank you. Do you have water? -Yes.
听说几天前这里有地震
We heard there was an earthquake up here a few days ago.
-真的吗？ -是啊
-ls that right? -Yes.
-家里还好？ -很好，谢谢
-Your family? -Yeah, all fine. Thank you.
-你想喝的话，我们有羊奶 -那太好了
-We have goat's milk, if you'd like.
-That would be fine.
那现在
Now,
如果我们把帐棚架在那里，就不会挡到你们的路了
if we set our tent away over there,
we'd be out of your way over there.
可以
That's fine.
露丝，过来帮忙，拿水给他们
Ruth! Help these men and bring them some water.
不行，H.W
No! H.W.
普兰优先生，你现在想喝羊奶吗？
Mr. Plainview, would you like that milk now?
-好的，谢谢 -玛丽，拿些羊奶来给他们
-That would be fine. Thank you.
-Mary! Bring them some milk.
我的家人会帮你架好你的帐棚
My family will help you set up your tent.
不，我们露营要自己动手
No, please. We set ourselves on this camping trip.
我们自己来架帐棚
We have to do the camping.
动作快
Hurry up!
-你有面包吗？ -我们有马铃薯
-Do you have bread? -We have potatoes.
马铃薯就很好了，谢谢
Potatoes would be nice, thank you.
我会叫她们煮些马铃薯给你们
l'll have them boil you up some potatoes.
没关系，我们可以生火来煮
That's all right. l thought maybe we'd make a fire.
我想跟我儿子一起合作生火
l wanted to work with my son on making a fire.
我儿子伊莱会拿些柴来给你们
All right. My son, Eli, will bring you some wood.
谢谢你盛情的招待，桑德先生
Thank you so much for your hospitality, Mr. Sunday.
-没问题 -我们不会碍事
-Yes. -And we'll be out of your way.
只是来猎鹌鹑
-We're just hunting for quail. -Yes.
-抱歉我们没有面包 -没关系
-l'm sorry we don't have any bread.
-No, no, no.
这里种不出玉米，全是石头
Corn doesn't fill out in the hills here. lt's mostly rock.
我们没地方可以种谷子
We don't have room to raise the grain.
谢谢你，小姐
Thank you, young lady.
我叫伊莱
My name is Eli.
是的，你是...伊莱桑德
Yes, you're Eli Sunday.
欢迎你们
Welcome.
-H.W. -伊莱
-H.W. -Eli.
-你们来猎鹌鹑？ -是的
-You're hunting quail? -That's right.
-我们会拿晚餐过来 -谢谢，真感谢你
-We will bring dinner. -Thank you. Thank you so much.
爸!
Dad!
看我的鞋子
Dad, look at my shoe.
那是地震震出来的油，别激动
That's earthquake oil. Set loose.
所以...
So...
所以？
So?
是啊，所以
So, so.
这里若有油，我们就运到海边
If there's anything here, we take it to the sea.
拉输油管到怀尼米港或圣宝拉
What we do is we build a pipeline
to Port Hueneme or Santa Paula,
大约有一百哩
it's about 100 miles,
我们再跟联合石油谈交易，这一行就是这样
and we do a deal with Union Oil. This is what we do.
之后我们就不需要铁路还有运送成本了
Then we don't need the railroads
and their shipping costs anymore.
懂吧？
You see?
懂
Yeah.
-你懂了？ -我懂
-You see that? -Yeah.
那样我们就能赚钱，赚大钱
Then we're making money. We're making the real money.
那也是我们该赚的
What we should be making. Not just...
不是把赚的钱浪费在运送上
Not just throwing it away on shipping costs.
那样赚的就太少了
Otherwise, it's just mud.
我们要付他们多少？
How much are we going to pay them?
他们是谁？
Who's that?
桑德家
The Sunday family.
我不会给他们油田价
l'm not going to give them oil prices.
我会给他们鹌鹑价
l'll give them quail prices.
我想跟你们谈一下
lf we could take a few minutes,
有件事我想跟你谈谈
there's something l'd very much like to talk with you about.
孩子的妈，带女孩子们出去
Mother, would you take the girls outside, please?
我说话不喜欢拐弯抹角
l believe in plain speaking, so...
这牧场很美，我喜欢猎鹌鹑
This is a beautiful ranch. l love hunting for quail.
我儿子有病，他需要新鲜空气
My boy has been sick, you know. He needs fresh air.
医生说他需要大量的新鲜空气
Doctors all say he needs plentiful fresh air.
那
So,
你想这块地的值多少钱？
what would you say would be
a fair price for this lot, Abel?
-买下这里？ -是的
-To buy this place? -That's right.
想一下
Take a moment.
- 对不起，我不知道 - 一备六元
-l'm sorry. l don't know. -Six dollars an acre.
六元？谢谢，伊莱
Six dollars? Thank you, Eli.
还有加上多年来 用来改良牧场的五百元
And then with the improvements
to the ranch over the years at $500...
我想出三千七买这个牧场
l'd like to offer you $3,700 for this ranch.
-就是三千七百元 -不行
-That's $3,700. -No.
上帝派这人来此，伊莱
The Lord has sent this man here, Eli.
是的，我相信是的
Yes, l believe He has.
-我出价三千七百元 -是什么引你来此的？
-My offer to you is $3,700.
-What is it that brought you here, sir?
万能上帝的指引
The Good Lord's guidance.
当然，之后我们可以租地给你
-Now, of course, within that... -What about our oil?
...we're going to develop a lease.
-你说呢？ -那我们的石油呢？
-What's that? -What about our oil?
什么石油？
What about it?
我们这里有石油，那很值钱
We have oil here. That's worth something.
你们有人会钻探石油？
Do you have someone who can drill for it?
-你认为这里有石油？ -我相信有
-Do you think there's oil here? -l know there is.
钻油费用是很昂贵的
lt's very expensive to drill.
把油从地底弄出来，你试过吗？
To get it up and out of the ground.
You ever tried that before?
-那要多少钱？ -很贵
-How much is it? -Costly.
我们的油在地上就有
Well, our oil sits right up on top of the ground.
我想那是渗出来的
l believe that's called seepage.
并不必然意味底下有东西
Doesn't necessarily mean there's anything underneath.
-你出多少钱买油？ -我不知道
-What would you give us for it? -l don't know.
-你也有不知道的 -是啊
-Something you don't know. -That's right.
你要多少？
What would you like, Eli?
一万
Ten thousand dollars.
为什么？
For what?
为了我的教堂
For my church.
有趣
That's good.
真是有趣
That's a good one.
那
Well...
要是我们决定钻探石油，若油井量产
lf we decide to drill for oil and if the well begins to produce,
我就给你的教堂五千元的签约金
l'll give your church a $5,000 signing bonus.
一万
Ten thousand.
你想找别人来这里钻油？
Do you want to find someone else
that's going to come here and drill, Eli?
找别人投资兼做苦工？
Make the investment and do
all the hard work that goes into it?
我去别的牧场也能猎鹌鹑
l can just as easily hunt for quail
on another ranch as l can here, so...
虽然我很乐意支持你的教堂
Though l'll happily be a supporter
of your church for as long as l can.
只有红利
For the bonus only.
很巧的是，我刚好在钻油业有认识人
Now, as it happens, l do have some
connections in the drilling business
他们也许能帮我们起头。你觉得如何，亚伯？
who might help get us started.
How do you feel about this, Abel?
好，伊莱说什么都好
Yes. What Eli says.
很好，我们先签个约来试试
Well, good! Let's draw up
some contracts and let's... Let's give it a try.
多谢你的帮忙，伊莱
Appreciate your help with this, Eli.
-午安 -午安
-Good afternoon. -Good afternoon.
-仲介？-对
-Real estate? -Yes.
是的，我想跟你谈谈
Yes, l'd like to talk to you.
我在找土地，我刚买下桑德牧场
l'm looking for some land. l just bought the Sunday ranch.
然后...地图在哪？
And, well, where's the map?
桑德牧场后的丘陵地在哪？
Where are the hills behind the Sunday ranch?
在这里，那是班迪的地。他有六百多备
That's here. lt's the Bandy tract. He has over 600 acres.
班迪，六百备
Bandy, 600.
-这里呢？ -毛德、布洛杰、瑞狄、卡尔
-What about this?
-A.C. Maude, Blodget, Redlick, Carr.
-现在的地租多少？ -一备六元
-What's it held at? -Six dollars an acre.
六元
Six.
这里呢？
What about this?
北文家的，那很好买，我保证
That's the Belvins', and that could be got, l'm sure.
这附近的地都能买下吗？
Can everything around here be got?
行
Sure.
保罗桑德成了我们的好朋友
Paul Sunday turned out to be a good friend of ours.
没错
That's right.
你尽快赶到这里，把佛雷英格带来
Well, you get here just as soon
as you can. Bring Fred English.
好了
Good enough.
谢谢
Thank you, porter.
-H.W.，你好吗？ -很好，你呢？
-H.W., how are you? -Fine, and you?
- 很不错，你爸呢？- 他在里面
-Pretty good. Where's your dad? -He's inside.
你们从西诺丘大老远赶来了
You fellas are a long way from Signal Hill.
-你好，普兰优 -你好，金
-Hello, Plainview. -Hello, Gene.
-真高兴见到你 -查理
-Good to see you. -Charlie.
-要去别的地方？ -经过，四处看看
-On your way somewhere else?
-Passing through. Looking around.
-看到你真怪 -是很怪，不是吗？
-Funny to see you. -Funny, isn't it?
你们是标准的家族事业
You boys are a regular family business.
你们来的有点晚了
You boys are a little late.
-你找到什么了？ -我找到一些有趣的东西
-What did you find?
-l found some interesting prospects.
听说标准石油买地了？
Did you hear Standard bought up?
-大多是北边的地 -我听说的也是
-Mostly in the north, so far.
-That's what l hear.
金，如果你想买地，往东去
l'm gonna tell you, Gene,
if you're gonna make a play, look east.
我宁可是你买下那里。这附近的地都被买下了
l'd rather it be you than someone else.
This mud around here has been taken.
有这个小帅哥在身边，谈买卖一定更顺利
lt must be easy when you have such
a cute face to carry around with you.
-你是想说我儿子很帅？ -正是
-Telling me how handsome my son is?
-Well, that l am.
你真好，谢谢，祝你好运
That's very nice. Thank you. Good luck, Gene.
-保重 -我说过，往东边去
-Take care. -Like l said, go east.
H.W.
你若要签约，可以找我当律师
l'll be your lawyer if you need to draw up a contract.
我能确保你不会被骗，帮你弄到你爸一半的利润
Make sure you don't get swindled, boy.
Get half what your dad's making.
怎样？
How's that?
那些人在干嘛？
What are those men doing?
他们是帮我们工作的人
They're just guys that are working for us.
他们只是四处看看
They're just looking around.
我们能赚多少钱？
How much money can we make?
不知道，要看情况
l don't know. lt depends.
一千元？
One thousand dollars?
玛丽说若她不祷告，她爸就打她
Mary said that her father beats her if she doesn't pray.
玛丽，年纪比较小的那个？
Mary, she's the smaller one?
对，就是她
Yes, she is.
-都到齐了？ -非常成功
-Everyone here? -Very successful.
可是？
But?
有几块地找不到地主
There were a few vacant lots
and one holdout.
-是谁的？ -威廉班迪
-Who? -William Bandy.
他是谁？
...eight. Who's he?
他在这里务农
He's an old man who homesteaded here.
跟孙子一起住，他想跟你谈谈
Lives with his grandson. He said he'd like to speak with you.
他来了？
ls he here?
不，他要你去找他
No, he'd like you to come visit with him.
他要抬高价钱
He's boosting his price.
他说他想跟收买土地的人谈
He said he'd like to speak with whoever is doing the buying.
让他等着，他会找上门的，走吧
Well, let him wait. He'll come around. Let's go.
各位？
Ladies and gentlemen?
各位
Ladies and gentlemen.
谢谢你们今晚大驾光临
Thank you so much for visiting with us this evening.
我跨越了大半的北达克达州来到这里，来看看这块土地
Now, l've traveled across half our state
to be here and to see about this land.
我敢说你们有人可能听说过
Now, I daresay some of you might have heard
一些更夸张的谣言，传说我有些什么计划
some of the more extravagant rumors
about what my plans are,
我只是认为你们该亲耳听我说
so I just thought you'd like to hear it from me.
就是这张脸，没什么神秘的
This is the face. It's no great mystery.
我是个石油商人，各位
I'm an oilman, ladies and gentlemen,
我对许多地方都有兴趣
I have numerous concerns spread across this state.
我有很多油井每天产出数千桶油
I have many wells flowing
at many thousand barrels per day,
所以我认为我是个石油商
so I like to think of myself as an oilman.
身为石油商
As an oilman, I hope that you'll forgive
我希望各位原谅我有话直说
just good old-fashioned plain speaking.
我们做的是家族事业
Now, this work that we do
is very much a family enterprise.
我跟我儿子H.W.携手合作
I work side by side with my wonderful son, H. W.
我想你们有人可能见过他了
I think one or two of you might have met him already.
我也鼓励我的手下带家人一起来
And I encourage my men to bring their families, as well.
当然，这么做有助于促进他们获得更有价值的人生
Of course, it makes for an ever
so much more rewarding life for them.
家庭代表孩子，孩子代表教育
Family means children, and children means education.
所以，不管我们落脚何处，教育是必要的
So, wherever we set up camp, education is a necessity,
我们也很高兴能满足需求
and we're just so happy to take care of that.
让我们在小波士顿造一间学校
So let's build a wonderful school in Little Boston.
这些孩子是我们努力的未来
These children are the future that we strive for,
所以他们也该拥有最好的
and so they should have the very best of things.
现在，还有一件事
Now, something else,
请别误会我有侮蔑的意思：面包
and please don't be insulted
if l speak about this. Bread.
我们来谈谈面包吧
Let's talk about bread.
在我看来，我很讨厌去想到
Now, to my mind, it's an abomination to consider
有任何男人、女人、或小孩，在我们这个伟大的国家里
that any man, woman, or child
in this magnificent country of ours
竟然将一条面包视为是奢侈品
should have to look upon a loaf of bread as a luxury.
我们要在这里挖水井，而水井就代表灌溉
We're going to dig water wells here,
and water wells means irrigation.
灌溉就意味着耕种
Irrigation means cultivation.
我们要在这里种谷子，在这之前一片荒芜的土地上
We're going to raise crops here where
before it just simply wasn't possible.
你们会有更多的谷子可以运用
You're going to have more grain
than you'll know what to do with,
面包会多到你吃不完，夫人
and bread will be coming right out of your ears, ma'am.
新的道路、农业、就业、教育
New roads, agriculture, employment, education.
这些只是改进的一小部份
These are just a few of the things we can offer you,
各位，我向你们保证
and l assure you, ladies and gentlemen,
若我们真在此找到石油
that if we do find oil here,
我想我们很有可能会找到
and l think there's a very good chance that we will,
你们的社区将不再贫瘠，它将兴隆繁盛
this community of yours
will not only survive, it will flourish.
我很乐意回答任何问题，请说？
l'd be happy to answer any questions
that you might have. Yes?
新的道路会通往教堂吗？
Will the new road lead to the church?
那会是第一个通往的地方。谢谢你，伊莱，还有谁？
That'll be the first place that it leads.
Thank you, Eli. Anyone else?
如果有任何事，我很容易找的
Well, if anything comes up, l'm pretty easy to find.
你们随时可以来找我
You just come visit with me.
谢谢各位宝贵的时间，晚安
Thank you so much for your time, and good night.
“何等权利能将万事”
What a privilege to carry
“来到耶稣座前求”
everything to God in prayer!
“何等权利能将万事”
What a privilege to carry...
只要沿着通往教堂的新路
Just follow the new road
right to the church.
新的路会引领你们过去
The new road will lead you there.
兄弟，你好，我叫伊莱
Hello, brother, my name is Eli.
第三启示教堂欢迎你
The Church of the Third Revelation
welcomes you.
兄弟，你好，我叫伊莱
Hello, brother, my name is Eli.
第三启示教堂欢迎你
The Church of the Third Revelation
welcomes you.
沿着新路走就能抵达教堂
Just follow the new road
right to the church.
“我们弱点主都知透”
Jesus knows our every weakness
“放心到主座前求”
Take it to the Lord in prayer
“劳苦多愁软弱不堪”
Are we weak and heavy-laden
“挂虑重担压肩头”
Cumbered with a load of care?
“主是你我避难处所”
Precious Savior still our refuge
“快到主恩座前求”
Take it to the Lord in prayer...
-丹尼尔，我能跟你谈谈吗？ -可以，请进
-Daniel, may l speak with you?
-Yes, come in.
他们一到我就带过来
l'll bring them up when they arrive.
-早 -早
-Good morning. -Good morning.
工程进度如何？
How is all the work coming?
很顺利
Everything's good.
-人手充足？ -当然
-All the men are provided for? -Of course.
充满干劲
Spirits seem high.
有什么需要我帮忙的吗？
ls there anything that you need from me?
-任何教堂能帮得上的忙？ -我想没有，谢谢
-Anything the church can do for you?
-l don't believe so. No. Thank you.
我知道你明天邀请大家
l understand you've asked the people to gather around
来此观看开井仪式
and watch the well begin tomorrow. ls that right?
- 是 - 我会为这口井祈福
-That's right. -l will bless the well.
在你开始之前，你该介绍我
Before you begin, you should introduce me.
你会看到我走向油井，然后...
You'll see me walk up
towards the oil well, and when l...
是油井塔
The derrick.
你会看到我走出来，然后你可以说出我的名字
You'll see me walk up,
and then you could say my name.
你走出来？
When you walk up?
对，你会看到我走出来，然后你可以说...
Yes. You'll see me walk up,
and then you could say,
“看顾上帝子民的本土之子”
''The proud son of these hills
who tended his Father's flock,''
然后你可以说出我的名字
and then you could say my name.
很好
That's fine.
-接着会怎样？ -接着我们就开始钻油
-And what happens then?
-Well, then we start the drill.
这是简单的祈福，不过却很重要
lt's a simple blessing, Daniel, but an important one.
只有几句话，不会太久
lt's just a few words. lt won't take long.
-什么时候？ -你们什么时候方便？
-What time? -What time's good for you, Eli?
-四点 -那就四点吧
-4:00. -Well, let's make it 4:00 then.
-很感谢你来访 -祝你愉快，谢谢
-My thanks for your visit. -Good day. Thank you.
各位午安
Afternoon, everyone.
跟我来
Come with me.
感谢各位在这个时刻来访
l thank you all so much for visiting with us at this time.
我很荣幸见过你们其中几位
l've had the pleasure of meeting some of you
希望接下来的日子里
and l hope very much in the months to come,
我能拜访你们每一个人
l'll be able to visit with each and every one of you.
我擅长钻凿却不善演说
l'm better at digging holes in the
ground than making speeches,
所以今晚略过演说
so let's forget the speech for this evening,
直接祈祷吧
just make it a simple blessing.
要明白，钻油不能只靠一个人
You see, one man doesn't prospect from the ground.
这要靠一整个社区的善良百姓，像各位
lt takes a whole community of
good people, such as yourselves,
而这很不错，我们齐聚一堂
and this is good. We stay together.
我们一起祷告、工作
We pray together, we work together,
若上帝对我们的努力微笑以待
and if the Good Lord smiles kindly on our endeavor,
我们就共享财富
we share in the wealth together.
在玛丽一号井开工前
Now, before we spud in Mary's Well Number One,
这井以我身旁的玛丽桑德命名
named for the lovely
Miss Mary Sunday, here by my side,
在地的本土之女
a proud daughter of these hills,
我想说，上帝保佑真诚的工人，当然，还有
l'd just like to say God bless these
honest labors of ours, and, of course,
上帝保佑各位
God bless you all.
阿门
Amen.
去吧
Now go.
很快就开始
Won't be a minute.
快点，H.W
Fast as you can, H.W.
准备好了？
Are you ready to do this?
动工了，各位
That's it, ladies and gentlemen!
艾尔罗斯很慷慨的为这个典礼自掏腰包的
Al Rose has very generously provided
some refreshments for this occasion
提供了一些点心，谢谢你
out of his own pocket. Thank you, Al.
请各位自便，我马上回来
lf you'll all just care to help yourselves,
l'll be back in a minute.
玛丽
Mary.
玛丽桑德
Mary Sunday.
-你喜欢你的新衣服吗？ -喜欢，谢谢
-Do you like your new dress?
-Yes. Thank you.
不用客气，我就觉得你会喜欢
You're welcome. l thought you'd like it.
-你高兴我来这里吗？ -高兴
-Are you happy l came here? -Yes.
你爸没再打你了吧？他有吗？
Your daddy doesn't hit you anymore,
does he? Does he now?
最好是没有，对吧？
Better not, right?
我会照顾你的
l'll take care of you.
不再被打了，对吧？不再被打了，去吧
No more hitting, right? No more hitting. Now go.
去多玩一下，不用再回来了
Go and play some more
and don't come back.
丹尼尔？
Daniel?
没事，H.W.，回去睡吧。去吧，快回去睡
lt's okay, H.W. Go back to sleep.
Go on. Go back to sleep.
丹尼尔
Daniel.
Daniel!
丹尼尔
怎样？
What?
井里死了一个人
Lost a man down the well.
-哪一个？ -乔根达
-What man? -Joe Gundha.
-我认识他吗？ -不认识
-Did l know him? -No.
怎么回事？
What happened?
拉起来
Pick it up.
拉刹车
Set the brake.
-绑起来 -绑好
-Tie it down. -Tie it on.
糟了
Shit!
该死，遗体呢？
God damn it. Where's the body?
-他们正在找 -好
-They're fishing it out now. -All right.
-钻头呢？ -在台子上
-Where's the bit? -lt's on the deck.
清理一下，帮他换衣服
Clean him up. Put some clothes on him.
然后
And...
架设一顶帐棚
Set up a tent.
任何人下去井里都要通知其他人，明白吗？
Anyone goes down into the cellar,
you tell somebody. Yes?
- 是 - 是，老板
-Yes, sir. -Yes, sir.
中午以前停工
Shut down till midday.
我看到了，是的，昨晚，我看到了
And l had a vision. Yes, last night, l had a vision
我感觉到上帝的气息贯穿我
and l felt God's breath move through me.
沉入我的胃
And it rolled down into my stomach.
它劈啪作响
lt sloshed around.
我的胃低语着，不是呐喊
And my stomach spoke in a whisper, not a shout,
“用手抚摸这位女士并抚慰她”
''Touch this woman with your hands
and caress her.'' Yes.
亲爱的杭特太太
My dear Mrs. Hunter,
你有关节炎，对吧？
you have arthritis, don't you?
-是的，伊莱 -好
-Yes, l do, Eli. -Yes.
恶魔在你手上，我会把它拉出来
The devil is in your hands, and l will suck it out.
我不会激动的把这恶魔扔出去
Now, l will not cast this ghost out with a fever
因为在我体内的神灵告诉我，我有新的沟通方法
for the new spirit inside me has shown
me l have a new way to communicate.
就是轻柔的低语
lt is a gentle whisper.
离开吧，恶鬼
Get out of here, ghost.
离开这里，恶鬼
离开
Get out.
离开这里，恶鬼
Get out of here, ghost.
-快进入这位女士的身体 -离开这里，恶鬼
-...and enter this woman's body now.
-Get out of here, ghost.
离开这里，不准你再转身回来
Get out of here. Don't you dare turn
around and come back.
你若胆敢回来
For if you do,
我会用全身神力给你迎头痛击
all the armies of my boot will kick you in the teeth
而你会被扔出去，丢进泥土里
and you will be cast up and thrown in the dirt
一屁股跌回地狱
and thrust back to perdition!
只要我牙齿还在，我要咬穿你
And as long as l have teeth, l will bite you,
就算我没牙齿，也会咬紧双颚
and if l have no teeth, l will gum you!
只要我拳头还在，我会痛揍你
And as long as l have fists, l will bash you!
滚吧，恶鬼!快离开这里!
Now, get out of here, ghost! Get out of here, ghost!
滚出去，恶鬼
Get out of here, ghost!
它走了
And it left!
哈利路亚!
-Hallelujah! -Hallelujah!
-赞美主和他的节日 -赞美上帝
-Praise the Lord and His holy days! -Praise God!
-阿门!谢谢 -感谢您，耶稣，感谢你，上帝
-Amen! Thank you.
-Thank you, Jesus. Thank you, God.
亲爱的杭特太太
My dear Mrs. Hunter.
跟我一起跳舞吧
Dance with me.
-感谢莅临 -真精彩的讲道
-Thanks for coming. -lt was a wonderful sermon.
-明天你会来吗？ -会的
-Will l see you tomorrow? -Yes.
伊莱
Eli.
昨晚井里发生悲剧
Had a tragedy at the well last night.
我听说了
Yes, l heard.
乔根达是虔诚的信徒
Joe Gundha was a man of considerable faith.
如果你想为他祈祷，他的葬礼是明天中午
So if you wish to say a few words,
his burial is at noon tomorrow.
丹尼尔，这场意外原本可以避免
Daniel, this accident could have been avoided.
那口井真令人遗憾
lt is terrible to think of that well
- 他们连续工作... - 这些人轮12小时的班
-working away out there...
-These men work in 12-hour shifts.
-没有获得祈福 -他们需要休息
-...unblessed. -They need their rest.
没休息，就会犯错
lf they don't have it,
they start to make stupid mistakes.
我看过他们喝酒
l've seen the men drinking.
那有关系吗？
Don't you think that has something to do with this?
这些人需要好好休息
We need these men well-rested to bring in this well.
如果他们听你讲道就不能休息
They can't get that if they're up here
listening to your gospel,
油井就没办法产油...更没办法让大家发财
and then the well can't produce
and blow gold all over the place.
我真希望跟乔多相处些时日
l wish l had more time with Joe Gundha.
该多做些什么的
More could have been done.
那么那口井就不能产油，也不能让大家发财
Then the well can't produce
and blow gold all over the place.
请你帮忙把他的私人物品
Now, would you see to it that his personal possessions
送还给他的家人，好吗？
find their way back to his family, please?
谢谢
Thank you.
听说你计划改建？
Heard you were planning some renovations.
对，信众数目成长惊人
Yes, our congregation is growing strongly.
-需要更多空间 -刚刚的表演真他妈的精彩
-We need more room.
-That was one goddamn hell of a show.
很高兴有你来访，丹尼尔
We were happy to have you, Daniel.
瓦斯、瓦斯!
Gas, gas, gas!
严禁火花!在这等着!
Lights out! Wait here. Wait here. Lights out!
把火灭了
Put that fire out!
他受伤了吗？H.W.! 把他抱下来给我
ls he hurt? H.W.! Hand him down to me!
-抱下来 -来了
-Hand him down! -Here.
-抱好了？ -我抱好了
-Got him? -l've got him!
天哪
Oh, God.
拜托
Come on.
开门
Open the door.
放手，很好，你很安全
Let go. There you go. You're safe. You're safe.
你很安全，我抱着你，你很安全，放手，儿子
You're safe now. l got you here.
You're safe. Let go, son.
告诉我哪里会痛...哪里会痛
Tell me where it hurts.
Tell me where it hurts. Tell me where...
-你看到事情经过了？ -没有
-Did you see this? -No.
告诉我哪里会痛
Tell me where it hurts.
你哪里会痛？
Where does it hurt you? Where does it hurt you?
-我听不见 -你撞到头了？
-l can't hear my voice. -Were you hit in the head?
你是不是撞到头了？告诉我!你撞到头要跟我说!
Were you hit in the head? Tell me!
You have to tell me if you were!
我听不见
l can't hear my voice.
我得去解决事情，你在这等我
l have to go and deal with this now.
You wait here for me.
你明白吗？在这等我，我马上回来，就一下子
You understand? You wait here for me.
l'll be back. l'll be back in a minute.
-在这等着 -不要走
-Wait here. -Don't leave!
我会照顾你的，在这等着，儿子，我要去灭火
l'm going to take care of you. Wait.
Stay here, son. l'm going to fix this.
-不要走 -你不会有事的
-Don't leave! -You're going to be fine!
在这等着
Wait for me here!
-抱住他、抱住他 -不要走
-Hold him down. Hold him down. -Don't leave!
切断绳索，丹尼尔
Got to break the cables, Daniel!
给我锤子
Get me a hammer!
给我一把锤子
在这里
Here you go.
退后
Get back!
-麦可 -老板
-Michael! -Sir!
带戴维和两个人
Take Dave and two of the fellas,
pick up some hoses...
比利，保护屋顶，太烫就离开
Billy, protect the roof.
Don't wait before it gets too hot.
你干嘛满脸愁容？
What are you looking so miserable about?
我们脚下有无尽的藏油
There's a whole ocean of oil under our feet!
除了你，没人能帮我挖出来
No one can get at it except for me.
H.W.还好吧？
H.W. okay?
他不好
No, he isn't.
-他在哪里？ -餐厅
-Where is he? -Mess room.
好了，别叫了，H.W
That's enough now.
That's enough, H.W. That's enough.
你听得见吗？听得见我说话吗？
Do you hear me? Can you hear me in there?
好了
That's enough.
-抓住他的腿 -我抓好了
-Grab his legs. -l have his legs.
-不，不行 -不，孩子
-No. Nope. -No, lad.
把那给我
Give me that.
别动，很好
Steady. That's it.
-冷静点，孩子 -很快就好了
-Easy, boy. Easy. -Soon be over.
很好，现在换另一边，把他转过来
Yeah, and that's good.
Now the other side. Turn him over.
快好了
Almost done.
好了
That's it.
过来，好了，都好了
Come here. lt's over. lt's over.
我们在旧金山或洛杉矶
Who do we know in San Francisco
有认识谁可以帮忙
or Los Angeles, who could work with...
你知道，我们可以找个人...帮H.W.找个老师
You know, we could... Someone, a teacher for H.W.
你要怎么找？
How could you figure out that?
打个电话给...该死，他叫什么来着？
Now, call...God damn it, what's his name?
旧金山的鲍伯布洛迪？
Bob Brody in San Francisco?
打给他，找个人下来
Call Bob Brody and get someone down here.
我马上打
l'll do it right away.
我们什么时候可以拿到钱？
When do we get our money, Daniel?
你不是治疗者吗？你不是神灵选中的人？
Aren't you a healer? And a vessel for the Holy Spirit?
你何时要来让我儿子恢复听力？
When are you coming over and make my son hear again?
你做不到？
Can't you do that?
若让我为井祈福，这就不会发生
lf you had let me bless the well,
this wouldn't have happened.
-丹尼尔 -你不该这么做的
-Daniel. -You shouldn't have done that.
你欠第三启示教堂5千元
You owe the Church of the Third Revelation $5,000
这是我们谈妥的交易条件之一
as part of the arrangement that we made!
别想跟我斗，小矮子! 敢到这里来闹事
Don't even try it, you little runt!
You splash around in here.
就是这样
That's it, that's it.
我要把你埋到地下
l'm going to bury you underground, Eli.
l'm going to bury you underground.
你是个笨蛋，亚伯
You are a stupid man, Abel.
你引狼入室来占我们便宜
You've let someone come in here
and walk all over us.
你让他来，在这里开挖石油
You let him in and do his work here,
你这个笨蛋却廉价贱卖土地
and you are a stupid man for what we could have had.
我遵照上帝旨意，我试过
l followed His word, Eli. l tried.
你啥都没做，只是呆坐家中
You didn't do anything but sit down.
你既懒又蠢
You're lazy, and you're stupid.
你想上帝会为你的愚蠢拯救你？
Do you think God is going to save you for being stupid?
他不救愚蠢的人
He doesn't save stupid people, Abel.
我要为你做的事扯烂你，笨蛋
l will tear you apart for
what you've done, you stupid man!
他怎么会来？你真的知道吗？
How did he come here? Do you really know? l know!
-儿子，求你别这样 -安静!
-Son, don't do this, please! -Be quiet!
闭上你的嘴，亚伯! 都怪你那个笨儿子
Shut your mouth, Abel! lt was your stupid son!
是保罗叫他来的，我知道
lt was Paul who told him to come here. l know it.
他跑去找他，还说...
He went to him and he said,
“我愚蠢的父亲会卖出他的地”
''My stupid, weak father will give away his lots.
“去占他的便宜” 而你竟让这一切发生了
''Go and take him.'' And you let it happen.
真是一对呆瓜父子
A stupid father to a stupid son.
滚出去
Get out of there!
需要我效劳吗？
Can l help you?
丹尼尔？
Daniel?
-你是谁？ -我叫亨利
-Who's that? -My name is Henry.
什么事？
Yeah?
我是亨利
l'm Henry.
你需要我帮什么忙吗？
What can l do for you?
我是亨利普兰优，我来自方达勒克
l'm Henry Plainview. l'm from Fond du Lac.
我是你...同父异母的弟弟
l'm your brother, from another mother.
恩尼斯是我父亲
Ernest is my father.
你是谁？
Who are you?
亨利
Henry.
-玛莉布兰琪？那是你母亲？ -是的，没错
-Mary Branch? ls that your mother?
-Yes, sir, that's right.
我在报上看过你油井的报导，关于你的成功
l read about your gusher in the paper, about your success.
你听说我成功？就跑来要钱？
You heard about my strike? You just show up?
我们的父亲死了
Our father's dead.
我听说恩尼斯死了，我想找你
Ernest died, l heard. l wanted to find you.
什么时候？
When?
三个月前，我收到安娜贝的信
Three months ago. l got a letter from Annabelle.
我妹妹安娜贝？
My sister, Annabelle?
-她在哪里？ -还在家乡，方达勒克
-Where is she? -Still at home. Fond du Lac.
你大老远跑来跟我说这个？
You came all the way from Wisconsin to tell me this?
我从新墨西哥来的，我住过那里
l'm coming from New Mexico. l've been there.
我是来找你的
l came to find you.
你知道我的事吗？
Did you know about me?
你有身份证明吗？
Do you have identification?
你有这封信吗？
Do you have this letter?
-你是从哪里来的？ -新墨西哥州
-Where are you coming from? -From New Mexico.
我知道，那里的哪里？
Yes, l know, but from where?
银矿市，我在那里待过两年
Silver City. l've been there for two years.
我尝试过自己钻油好几年
l was trying drilling of my own for years.
-在德州、路易斯安那都租过地 -有什么成果吗？
-Getting leases in Texas. Louisiana.
-Anything that produced?
没有，不像你那么成功
No. Not like your success, no.
-你结婚没？ -没有
-Are you married? -No.
我坐过牢，我有过一段悲惨的日子
l spent time in jail. l had a stretch of very bad time.
身无分文，在路易斯安那被捕
l had nothing. l was picked up in Louisiana.
我在外役监服役半年修筑马路
l worked on a chain gang for six months building roads.
那一段日子...很辛苦
That was a very hard time.
你结婚没？
Are you married?
你为什么会坐牢？
What were you in jail for?
信不信由你，我做了那么多糟糕的事
Believe it or not, for all the
terrible things l've gotten myself into,
但我被逮捕时，却啥都没做
when they picked me up, l hadn't done anything.
不过我做过许多事
But l've done my share of things
不该公开谈论
that shouldn't be talked about.
喝吧，喝掉
Drink it. Drink it!
睡吧
Come on.
所以...
So...
你要什么？
What do you want, Henry?
没什么
Nothing.
如果你能付我钱，我可以为你效劳
lf you can spare something, l can work for you in any way.
我知道我会继续前进，没多久就会回故乡去
l know l'll keep moving, before long,
to get back to Fond du Lac.
-你有钱吗？ -有一些
-Do you have any money? -Some.
-不多 -直接回答我
-Not much. -Just answer me directly.
没有，就说你想留下来工作
You say ''nothing,'' then you say
you'd like to stay and work.
更好的是，我希望听到你说你想留下来
And it's better, l'd just like to hear
you say you'd like to be here.
我想留下来
l'd like to be here.
我是个好工人。我做过钻油架、建过铁路
l'm a good worker. l worked cable tool rigs, built railroads.
我不需要帮忙
l won't need any favors.
很好
Good.
我母亲知道些什么？
What did my mother know?
我不知道
I don't know.
我不知她知不知道，换个角度想，也许她根本不知道
I don't know if she knew and looked
the other way, if she never knew.
你为何离开？
Why did you leave?
我知道你跟我们的爸爸处不好
I know you didn't get on with our father.
我为地理调查组织工作去了堪萨斯
l worked for Geological Survey and went to Kansas.
我在那待不下去，我就是没办法
l couldn't stay there. l just couldn't.
我不喜欢自我辩解
l don't like to explain myself.
-亨利，你很容易生气吗？ -气什么？
-Are you an angry man, Henry? -About what?
你嫉妒心重吗？你会嫉妒吗？
Are you envious? Do you get envious?
我不这么想，不会
l don't think so, no.
我天生爱出头
l have a competition in me.
我不要别人成功
l want no one else to succeed.
-我痛恨大部分的人 -那部份的我已经死了
-l hate most people. -That part of me is gone.
工作和不成功
Working and not succeeding,
所有的...失败都让我...
all my failures have left me...
我不在乎了
l just don't care.
如果我有，你就有
Well, if it's in me, it's in you.
我有时候看着人们，却看不到值得喜欢的特点
There are times when l look at people
and l see nothing worth liking.
我想赚到足够的钱，远离所有人
l want to earn enough money l can get away from everyone.
你要拿你的孩子怎么办？
What will you do about your boy?
我不知道
l don't know.
也许情况会改变
Maybe it'll change.
人的听力会恢复吗？我不知道，也许也没人知道
Does your sound come back to you?
l don't know. Maybe no one knows that.
-医生也许也不知道 -他母亲呢？
-Doctor might not know that. -Where's his mother?
我不想谈我的私事
l don't want to talk about those things.
我很清楚人性的黑暗面
l see the worst in people, Henry.
我不需要认识他们就能知道
l don't need to look past seeing them to get all l need.
多年来我逐渐的建立了我的仇恨感
l've built up my hatreds over the years, little by little.
你的到来给了我第二股能量
Having you here gives me a second breath of life.
我不能继续靠自己打拼
l can't keep doing this on my own
跟这些烂人
with these people.
丹尼尔!丹尼尔，醒醒!丹尼尔!
Daniel! Daniel, wake up! Daniel!
我要去跟车掌说句话
Just have to go and have a word with the conductor.
我马上回来
l'll be right back.
你待在这里，明白吗？待在这里
You stay here. You understand? You stay here.
我马上回来
l'll be right back.
不!不!
No! No!
不!
No!
-提佛 -普兰优
-Tilford! -Plainview.
这是我弟弟，亨利普兰优
This is my brother, Henry Plainview from Fond du Lac.
我是提佛，幸会
H.M. Tilford. Pleasure.
亨利普兰优...卡特
Henry Plainview. J.J. Carter.
那么...
So...
-开始吧？ -好的
-Shall we? -Yes.
你儿子好吗？
How's your boy?
-多谢你关心 -我们帮得上什么忙吗？
-Thank you for asking. -ls there anything we can do?
关心就够了
Thanks for asking is enough.
你有什么计划？
So what are your plans?
你们是想买我这里的土地？
ls this about buying up my tracts here?
对
Yes.
电报提的是我在灰狼坡的地
The cable was about my Coyote Hills lease.
-我们也想买那里 -灰狼坡的地你出价多少？
-We'd like that, too.
-What's your offer on Coyote Hills?
-我们出15万买所有的权利 -我接受，接下来呢？
-We'll offer 1 50,000 for full title.
-That's a deal. What's next?
你在小波士顿有一万一千备地。你有一口能产油的井
You have 11 ,000 acres in Little Boston.
You have one proven well
-先前出了事 -我有三口能产油的井
-that was damaged... -l have three wells proven.
你根本没查清楚，是三口井
You haven't been paying attention. That's three proven wells.
我们一分钟内就能让你成为富翁
We'll make you a millionaire while you're sitting here
from one minute to the next.
那我接下来要做什么？
And what else would l do with myself?
-你问我？ -我还能做什么？
-Are you asking me? -What else would l do with myself?
照顾你儿子
Take care of your son.
我不知道你要做什么
l don't know what you would do.
若你是我，标准石油花一百万
lf you were me and Standard
offered to buy what you had
买你所拥有的一切，为什么？
for a million dollars, why? So, why?
你知道原因
You know why.
你该自己去挖掘
Yeah, you fellas should just scratch around in the dirt
像我们一样找油，而不是买下别人的心血
and find it like the rest of us, instead of
buying up someone else's hard work.
我挖过，孩子
l've scratched around the dirt, son.
你要改变你的运输成本？
You going to change your shipping costs?
运送成本不由我们决定，是铁路
We don't dictate shipping costs. That's railroad business.
你们没买下铁路啊？
You don't own the railroads?
你们当然买下了
'Course you do. Of course you do.
你要把油运到哪里？
Where you going to put it all?
哪里？
Where?
建输油管？找联合石油？随便你
Build a pipeline? Make a deal
with Union Oil? Be my guest.
不过你若无法成功
But if you can't pull it off,
你脚下有再多油也卖不出去
you've got an ocean of oil
under your feet with nowhere to go.
何不卖给我们？我们能让你发财
Why not turn it over to us? We'll make you rich.
你就好好陪你儿子吧
You spend time with your boy.
这是个伟大的发现
lt's a great discovery.
让我们帮你吧
Now, let us help you.
你这是教我怎么经营我的家庭？
Did you just tell me how to run my family?
这可能比找到石油还重要
lt might be more important now
that you've proven the field
而我们想帮你
and we're offering to buy you out.
有一天我会去找你，摸进你家
One night l'm going to come to you,
inside of your house,
或你睡觉的地方，割了你的喉咙
or wherever you're sleeping,
and l'm going to cut your throat.
什么？
What?
你说什么？你疯了吗？
What are you talking about? Have you gone crazy?
-你听见我说的话了？ -我听见了
-Did you hear what l said? -l heard what you said,
- 你干嘛这么说？-不准你教我怎么养儿子
-why did you say it?
-You don't tell me about my son.
你干嘛抓狂又威胁要杀我？
Why are you acting insane
and threatening to cut my throat?
-不准你教我怎么养儿子 -我没教你任何事
-You don't tell me about my son.
-l'm not telling you anything!
我要你讲理，若有冒犯，我道歉
l'm asking you to be reasonable.
lf l've offended you, l apologize.
等着看我有何能耐吧
You'll see what l can do.
这一小块地是哈普拥有的三千备牧场
This parcel here is the 3,000-acre
ranch owned by B.L. Harper.
这是圣路易斯郡的土地
This is San Luis Obispo County land.
从这里到海边，都是联合石油的
And from here to the coast, it's all Union Oil.
这是什么？这怎么不是我的？
What's this? Why don't l own this?
-这怎么不是我的？ -那是班迪的地
-Why don't l own this?
-That's the Bandy tract.
我们在买地时，他拒绝出售
He was the holdout, when we were doing the buying.
他原本想跟你谈
He had hoped to speak with you.
不能在这块地附近建输油管吗？
Can't you just build the pipeline around this tract?
我能在第赫求庇山脉周围建五十哩的输油管吗？
Can l build around 50 miles of Tehachapi mountains?
别在我面前耍白痴
Don't be thick in front of me, Al.
-我可以再去找他 -不，我去跟那个人谈
-l can go to him again. -No, l'll go and talk to the man.
我去谈，让你看看怎么做才对
l'll talk to him. Show you how it's done.
好，打包行李吧，亨利
All right. Pack it up, Henry.
-他房间有多大？ -他跟另一个孩子住一间
-How big is his room?
-He's sharing with another boy.
-谁？ -比他大的孩子，大约12岁
-Who? -An older boy. About 1 2.
他已经待一年了，叫巴朗
He's been there for a year. Named Ballard.
-房间有多大？ -够大了，有足够的空间
-How big is the room?
-lt's a fair size. Got enough space.
你要带亨利去见联合石油的人？
Are you taking Henry with you to meet Union Oil?
-你是威廉班迪的儿子？ -孙子
-Are you the son of William Bandy? -Grandson.
-他在吗？ -他出去了
-ls he here? -No, he's out.
他人在哪里？
Where is he?
我说他出去了，你要干嘛？
Told you, he's out. Now, what do you want?
我叫丹尼尔普兰优，我想跟他谈谈他的地
l'm Daniel Plainview. l want to talk
with him about his property.
-谈什么？ -我想我会跟他当面谈
-About what? -l believe l'll talk with him about that.
-你就是那个石油商人？ -是的
-You're that oilman, aren't you? -That's right.
我们不要你来这里乱挖
We don't want you drilling out here.
我也不要，他什么时候回来？
l don't want it either. Now, when will he be back?
过几天
Few days.
告诉他我想跟他谈，不谈挖地
Tell him l'd like to speak with him. Not about drilling.
我一个礼拜后再来
And l'll be back in a week.
把那放进玻璃框里
Put that in a glass case.
敬联合石油
Here's to Union Oil.
数百哩的输油管
Hundred miles of pipeline,
和本国所有的个人油商
and all the independent producers of this great state.
干杯
Cheers.
方达勒克有间房子
There's that house in Fond du Lac
约翰霍利建的，你记得吗？
that John Hollister built. Do you remember it?
我小时候认为那是我看过的最美的房子
l thought as a boy that was
the most beautiful house l'd ever seen,
我想要它
and l wanted it.
我想住在里面
l wanted to live in it.
在里面吃饭
And eat in it.
清扫它
And clean it.
就算还只是个孩子，我也想让自己的孩子在附近奔跑
And even as a boy, l wanted
to have children to run around in it.
你现在想要什么都能拥有了
You can have anything you'd like now, Daniel.
你也该拥有
And you should.
-你想在哪里建房子？ -这里，也许吧，靠近海边
-Where are you going to build it?
-Here, maybe. Near the ocean.
你想建一栋一模一样的房子？
Would you make it look like that house?
我现在要是看到那栋房子会吐
l think if l saw that house now, it'd make me sick.
我们可以用餐，再找几个女人
We can eat and get some women.
带她们去桃树舞厅跳舞
Take them to the Peachtree dance.
我说灌醉她们再带她们去跳舞
l say get liquored up and take them
to the Peachtree dance.
好
Yeah.
你能给我一点钱吗？
Can l have some money, please?
我要你告诉我一件事
l want you to tell me something.
什么事？
What?
那房子旁边的牧场叫什么名字？
What's the name of the farm next to the Hill House?
What was the name of the farm next to the Hill House?
-我不记得了 -你是谁？
-l can't remember... -Who are you?
我会走的，丹尼尔
l'll leave, Daniel.
你是谁？
Who are you?
我谁都不是
l'm no one.
让我起来离开吧
Just let me get up and go.
我有弟弟吗？
Do l have a brother?
我在国王城认识一个人，他说他是你弟弟
l met a man in King City who said he was your brother.
我们当了几个月的朋友
We were friends for months.
在国王城工作
Working in King City.
他想设法来找你
And he wanted to make his way to you, Daniel.
我们身无分文
We didn't have any money.
他死于肺结核
He died of tuberculosis.
他没有遇害
He wasn't harmed.
不是他杀，没阴谋
Wasn't killed, nothing bad.
不过他跟我说过你的事
But he told me about you,
我只是用了他的故事
and l just took his story,
利用了他的日记
used his diary.
丹尼尔
Daniel.
丹尼尔，我是你朋友
Daniel, l'm your friend.
我并没有想伤害你
l'm not trying to hurt you.
从来没有
Never.
只想苟活
Just survive.
不!
No!
“我的哥哥...”
你是谁？
Who is it?
我是班迪
l'm Bandy.
是的、是的
Yes. Yes.
威廉班迪
William Bandy.
对，我想租用你的土地
Yeah, l'd like to lease your land.
我之前有请你来找我谈
l had asked for you to come and talk to me before.
当时你正在租地
When you were leasing land.
没错，是的
That's right, yes.
我儿子生了重病
My boy's been very sick, you know.
这是在你儿子生病之前
This was before your boy got sick.
我知道
你想在我的土地上建输油管
Now, l know that you would like to build a pipeline
through my property.
-我听说的没错吧？ -完全正确
-ls that right, what l've heard?
-lt's absolutely right. And,
这个
well...
八寸的油管，有你同意就可以埋设
Eight inch pipe. lt could be buried with your consent.
我向你保证绝对不会破裂
l guarantee you absolutely no disruption...
上帝
God.
上帝跟我说过你该怎么做
God has told me what you must do.
该怎么做呢？
And what is that?
你该接受耶稣基督的洗礼
You should be washed in the blood of Jesus Christ.
但我受洗过了
But l am.
我受洗过了，班迪先生
l have been washed, Mr. Bandy. l have been.
那是你救赎的唯一方法,也是你达成目标的唯一方法
lt's your only way to salvation.
And your only way for what you want.
你可以在第三启示教堂受洗
You can take it at the Church of the Third Revelation.
我付你三千元
l'll pay you $3,000.
我希望你成为我们教堂的一员
l'd like you to be part of our church.
我付你五千元
l'll pay you $5,000.
受洗吧
Be baptized.
免除你所犯下的罪行
Be forgiven for the sin that you've done.
你是说什么罪行，班迪先生？
What sin are you referring to, Mr. Bandy?
钻油的罪行？
My sin of drilling?
我真诚希望每个人都能获得救赎，你们不是吗？
I truly wish everyone could be saved, don't you?
是的
Yes.
可是恐怕并非如此
I am afraid that's just not the case.
普世救赎的教义是谎言，不是吗？
The doctrine of universal salvation is a lie, is it not?
-那是谎言 -那是谎言
-lt's a lie. -lt's a lie.
我希望每个人都能获得救赎，但并非如此，并非如此
l wish everyone could be saved, but they won't. No, they won't.
你永远不会获得救赎，如果你...
You will never be saved if you...
拒绝接受主
Reject the blood.
很好
Good.
现在，有罪人想获得救赎吗？
Now, is there a sinner here looking for salvation?
新的成员？
A new member?
我再问一次
l'll ask it again.
有罪人来此寻求上帝吗？
ls there a sinner here looking for God?
是的
Yes.
让我来
Allow me.
谢谢你的光临，丹尼尔兄弟
Thank you for coming, brother Daniel.
谢谢，伊莱
Thank you, Eli.
我们这里有个罪人，他希望获得救赎
We have a sinner with us here who wishes for salvation!
-丹尼尔，你是罪人吗？ -是的
-Daniel, are you a sinner? -Yes.
主上听不见你，丹尼尔
The Lord can't hear you, Daniel.
告诉他，去跟他说，没关系的
Say it to Him. Go ahead and speak to him. lt's all right.
-是的 -双膝跪地
-Yes. -Down on your knees.
向他祷告
Pray to Him.
仰望天空说出来
Look up to the sky and say it.
你要我说什么？
What do you want me to say?
你来到这里，带来良善和财富
Daniel, you've come here and
you've brought good and wealth,
可是也带来你的坏习惯
but you have also brought your bad habits as a backslider.
你勾引女性又遗弃孩子
You've lusted after women,
and you have abandoned your child.
你的孩子，你抚养又遗弃
Your child, that you raised, you have abandoned
只因他病了，因此你有罪
all because he was sick and you have sinned.
大声说吧，我是罪人
So say it now. l am a sinner.
-我是罪人 -大声一点
-l am a sinner. -Say it louder.
-我是罪人 -我是罪人
-l am a sinner. -l am a sinner.
大声点，丹尼尔!我是罪人!
Louder, Daniel! l am a sinner!
-我是罪人 -主啊，对不起
-l am a sinner. -l am sorry, Lord.
-主啊，对不起 -我要受洗
-l am sorry, Lord. -l want the blood.
-我要受洗 -你遗弃了你的孩子
-l want the blood. -You have abandoned your child.
我遗弃了我的孩子
l have abandoned my child.
-我将永远不再犯 -我将永远不再犯
-l will never backslide. -l will never backslide.
我曾迷失，但我现已觉醒
l was lost, but now l am found.
-我曾迷失，但我现已觉醒 -我遗弃了我的孩子
-l was lost, but now l'm found. -l have abandoned my child.
说出来，说啊
Say it. Say it.
-我遗弃了我的孩子 -大声说，说大声点
-l abandoned my child. -Say it louder. Say it louder!
我遗弃了我的孩子
l've abandoned my child!
l've abandoned my boy!
现在乞求受洗
Now beg for the blood!
让我受洗，让我离开这里
Just give me the blood, Eli. Let me get out of here.
让我受洗，主啊，让我离开
Give me the blood, Lord, and let me get away!
你接受耶稣基督成为你的主和救世主吗？
Do you accept Jesus Christ as your Lord and Savior?
-我接受 -滚出去吧，恶魔
-Yes, l do. -Get out of here, devil!
出去，恶魔!出去，罪衍!
Out, devil! Out, sin!
-让我感受主的力量 -你接受
-Let me feel the power of the Lord, Eli.
-Do you accept
第三启示教堂导引你吗？
the Church of the Third Revelation as your spiritual guide?
-滚出去，恶鬼 -你的主在哪里，伊莱？
-Get out of here, ghost! -Where is your Lord, Eli?
-滚出去，回你的巢穴去 -他在那里
-Get out! Go back where you belong!
-Where is he? There he is!
你接受基督成为你的救世主？
Do you accept Jesus Christ as your Savoir?
是的，我接受
Yes, l do.
“你是否愿从罪担得释放？”
Would you be free from the burden of sin?
“宝血有能力”
There's power in the blood
Power in the blood
“你是否愿战胜邪恶？”
Would you o'er evil a victory win?
输油管有谱了
There's a pipeline.
“耶稣的宝血有能力”
There's wonderful power in the blood
“真有权能，奇妙大权能”
There is power, power wonder-working power
“在羔羊宝血内”
In the blood of the Lamb
赞美主!
Praise the Lord!
欢迎加入教会，普兰优兄弟
Welcome to the fold, brother Plainview.
欢迎，丹尼尔兄弟，上帝保佑你
Welcome, brother Daniel. God bless you.
上帝保佑
God bless you.
- 哈利路亚 - 阿门
-Hallelujah. -Amen.
欢迎回家，兄弟
Welcome home, brother.
好了，够了
That's enough. That's enough, now.
他必须...自己接纳圣灵
He must take the spirit in on his own.
我们有了新成员
We have a new member.
-是的，兄弟 -哈利路亚
-Yes, brother. -Hallelujah.
-哈利路亚 -阿门
-Hallelujah. -Amen.
-我甜美的玛丽 -普兰优先生非常慷慨的
-My sweet Mary. -Mr. Plainview has been generous
捐献给教堂
enough to make a $5,000 donation
我们引颈企盼的5千元
to the church which we are still waiting for.
我真高兴，我真高兴
That does me good. That does me good.
欢迎回家，儿子
Welcome home, son.
这是乔治雷诺，启聪学校的老师
This here's George Reynolds.
Teacher from the deaf school.
- 普兰优先生 - 弗莱彻
-Mr. Plainview. -Fletcher.
这是乔治雷诺，启聪学校的老师
This here's George Reynolds.
Teacher from the deaf school.
- 普兰优先生 - 弗莱彻
-Mr. Plainview. -Fletcher.
我抱不动你了
You're too heavy for me.
你想吃点什么吗？
Do you want to get something to eat?
那是输油管，看到没？一路直达大海
That's the pipeline, see? All the way to the sea.
过来
Come here.
我爱你，儿子
l love you, son.
让我好好看看你
Let's take a look at you.
好了，够了、够了
All right. That's it, that's it. That's it.
我们帮你弄点好吃的吧
Let's get some decent food inside of you.
我们就需要这个, 好吃营养又昂贵的餐点
That's all we need here is a good, strong, expensive meal.
你饿了吗？
You hungry?
-服务生？ -是，先生
-Waiter? -Yes, sir.
两份牛排，一杯威士忌，给他水
Two steaks, a whiskey, and water for him.
-还有羊奶 -好的，先生
-And goat's milk. -Very good, sir.
我们要让这位老师帮你
We're going to have this teacher help you.
他会帮忙打理一切，懂吗？
He's going to help take care of all of this. Understand?
因为我需要你，需要你帮忙
'Cause l need you. Need your help.
一切条件都备齐了，过来
Got everything we need now
to build this company. Come here.
午安
Good afternoon.
-你好吗？ -很高兴再见到你
-How are you doing? -lt's nice to see you again.
-我们有四个人 -我马上准备
-We need four. -l'll have them right up.
-午安，丹尼尔 -你好，提佛
-Good afternoon, Daniel. -Tilford. Good afternoon.
-你好，我是提佛 -你不必用吼的
-Hello! H.M. Tilford! -You don't have to shout.
幸会
Pleasure.
小波士顿感觉很不错
lt's good to be in Little B.
-可以多种点树 -是啊
-Could use some rain out here. -Yeah, we could.
-来了 -伦敦烤肉好吃吗？
-There we go. -R.J., how's the London broil?
我们在这些人之前点饮料的
Believe we ordered these drinks before those people.
-说说看，伦敦烤肉好吃吗？ -抱歉，各位先生
-R.J., tell us. How's the London broil?
-Excuse me, gentlemen. Sorry.
对不起，我马上拿牛排过来
l am sorry about that, sir. l'll have your steaks right out.
-绿龟汤很棒 -是吗？
-So that green turtle soup is fantastic. -ls it?
好喝极了
lt's delicious.
听上去不错
Sounds good to me.
标准石油给我们一百万租用小波士顿的地
So Standard offered us a million
dollars for the Little Boston leases.
我跟提佛说他想都别想
l told H.M. Tilford where he could shove that.
我们跟联合石油谈妥了交易, 输油管!
And we made a deal with Union! On the pipeline!
还有我们地底下蕴藏的石油
And that whole ocean of oil underneath our fields.
-... 十五万 - 是
...$150,000. -Yes.
我们需要资金来开采
We needed the money to drill.
-这家伙是谁？ -我找过他
-Who is this guy? -l go out to meet him.
他挖到石油，我们想跟他谈交易
He's getting oil on the property.
We're trying to make a claim on it.
跟他开价一百万
Offered him a million dollars.
-他断然拒绝了 -我饿了
-Turned us down flat. -Well, l'm hungry.
橘子炸饼、马铃薯泥、青豆仁
Orange fritters, mashed potatoes, green peas.
-每人一份？ -我喜欢
-All the way around? -All right.
等等
Hold on.
我要你看看那边
l want you to look over there.
-丹尼尔，让我介绍一下... -看那边，看到没？
-Daniel, let me introduce... -Look over there. You see?
那是我儿子，看到他没？
That's my son. See him?
-看到了 -你看到了？
-Yes. -Do you see?
我看到他了
l see him.
别想教我怎么经营我的家庭
You don't tell me how to raise my family.
我说过别想教我怎么经营家庭
l told you not to tell me how to raise my family.
丹尼尔
Daniel...
你看到了什么？
So what do you see?
-交易的事我很替你高兴 -我跟联合石油谈成交易
-l'm very happy for you that the deal...
-Yes, l made a deal with Union.
-我儿子很高兴，他很安全 -恭喜了
-My son is happy. He's safe. -Congratulations.
-现在是我在照顾他，所以... -太好了
-l'm taking care of him now, so... -Excellent.
你看起来像个笨蛋，对吧？
You look like a fool, don't you, Tilford?
-对 -对
-Yes. -Yes.
对，你很像
Yes, you do.
抱歉，各位
Excuse me, gentlemen.
抱歉，各位，原谅他
Excuse me, gentlemen. Excuse him, gentlemen.
我跟你说过我会怎么做
l told you what l was going to do.
我的儿子
My son.
桑德先生，我知道你要离开这里
Mr. Sunday, l understand that you're leaving our fair community.
-是啊，我要去传教 -你要去哪？
-Yes, l'm going on a mission. -Where you going?
欧岱、塔福，之后去贝克尔斯菲
Oildale, Taft, and then on to Bakersfield.
我想让你知道...
Well, l want you to know...
欧岱、塔福，之后去贝克尔斯菲
Oildale, Taft, and then on to Bakersfield.
我想让你知道...
Well, l want you to know...
三刻钟时间
Three quarters of an hour.
你对我们贡献良多
...you done a great job for us.
-谢谢，你会出现在我的祈祷中 -非常感谢你
-Thank you. You will be in my prayers.
-l thank you very much.
联合石油公司，加州圣保拉
Union Oil Company, Santa Paula, California.
妇人对他说 “先生，请给我这水吧”
''The woman saith unto him, 'Sir, give me this water
1927年
“免得我再渴，也免得我再来这裹汲水”
'''and l shall thirst not, neither come hither to draw.'''
(向丹尼尔普兰优收取相同费用)
进来、进来
Come in, come in.
我们能单独谈谈吗？
Can we be alone?
这是我最亲近的伙伴，我什么都让他听
This is my closest associate. He hears everything.
-我想私下跟你谈 -你根本不会谈
-l'd prefer to speak to you in private. -You can't speak.
你何不一边挥你的手
So why don't you flap your hands about
一边要这家伙告诉我你去了哪里
and have what's-his-name tell me where you've been.
还是你以为我不知道？
Or do you think l don't know?
这让我很难开口
This is hard for me to say.
我先告诉你，我很爱你
l'll tell you first, l love you very much.
因为你，我学会喜爱我的工作
l've learned to love what l do because of you.
我要离开这里
l'm leaving here.
我要去墨西哥
l'm going to Mexico.
我要带玛丽一起走，去墨西哥
l'm taking Mary, and l'm going to Mexico.
我想念在户外的工作
l miss working outside.
我想念油田
l miss the fields.
只要一阵子
lt'll only be for a time,
让我自己去钻探石油
for me to do my own drilling
开始我自己的公司
and start my own company.
是时候...该做出改变了
lt's time to make a change.
这让你成为我的竞争对手
This makes you my competitor.
-不，不是那样的 -就是那样，孩子
-No. No, it's not like that. -lt is like that, boy.
你自己的公司？
Your own company, huh?
没错
That's right.
在墨西哥
ln Mexico?
是的
Yes.
你这是一大失策。为什么要这么做？
You are making such a misstep. So, what are you doing?
我知道你我许多事都意见相左
l know you and l have disagreed over many things.
我宁可你当父亲而不是事业伙伴
l'd rather keep you as my father than my partner.
那就说啊
Then say it.
如果你有话要跟我说，就说啊
lf you've got something to say to me, then say it.
我想听你而不是你的狗说
l'd like to hear you speak instead of your little dog.
我要带我太太去墨西哥
l'm going to Mexico with my wife.
我要离开你
l'm going away from you.
这并不难，对吧？
That wasn't so hard, was it?
以你的所作所为扼杀我们
Killing us with what you're doing.
你扼杀了我把你当儿子的形象
You're killing my image of you as my son.
你太顽固，不肯聆听
You are stubborn. You won't listen.
你不是我儿子
You're not my son.
别这么说，我知道你不是有意的
Please don't say that. l know you don't mean it.
这是事实，你不是我儿子，你一直都不是
lt's the truth. You're not my son. You never have been.
你是个...孤儿
You're an orphan!
你听过这个字眼吗？
Did you ever hear that word?
把我说的话告诉他
Tell him what l said.
你现在的行为就像孤儿
You operated here today like one.
我早该料想到这一天的
l should have seen this coming.
我早该知道的，过去这些年来
l should have known that,
under this all, these past years
你逐渐的建构了对我的仇恨
you've been building new hate for me, piece by piece.
我甚至不知道你是谁，因为你跟我一点都不像
l don't even know who you are
because you have none of me in you.
你是...别人的小孩
You're someone else's.
这样的愤怒、这样的存心不良
This anger. Your maliciousness.
跟我完全没关系
Backwards dealings with me.
你是沙漠中某个篮子里的孤儿
You're an orphan from a basket in the middle of the desert.
我认养你没别的理由，只因我需要一张小孩脸好买地
And l took you for no other reason
than l needed a sweet face to buy land.
你明白没？
Did you get that?
现在你知道了
So now you know.
看着我，你连废物都算不上
Look at me! You're lower than a bastard.
你跟我一点都不像，你只是某个篮子里的废物
You have none of me in you.
You're just a bastard from a basket.
感谢上帝我一点都不像你
l thank God l have none of you in me.
不是我儿子，只是一个没力的竞争对手
Not my son. Just a little piece of competition.
篮子里的废物
Bastard from a basket.
Bastard from a basket!
你是篮子里的废物
You're a bastard from a basket!
醒醒，丹尼尔先生
Get up, Mr. Daniel.
丹尼尔先生
Mr. Daniel.
丹尼尔先生，你有访客
Mr. Daniel, you've got a visitor.
醒醒，先生
Wake up, Mr. Daniel.
先生？
Sir?
你可以退下了
You can leave us now.
丹尼尔
Daniel.
丹尼尔普兰优的房子失火了!
Daniel Plainview, the house is on fire!
丹尼尔兄弟，我是伊莱
Brother Daniel, it's Eli.
是的，你是
Yes, it is. Yes, it is.
我弄点喝的吧
l'll make us a drink.
你家真神奇
Your home is a miracle.
真美
lt's beautiful.
上帝庇佑它
God bless it.
我四处传播他的话语
l've been spreading His word far and wide.
四处传播
Far and wide.
为他旅行各处
So much travel for Him.
我在广播电台做过
l've been working in radio.
发生了...发生了好多事
Yes, so much... So much has been happening.
到这里，找到你，看到你还好真的很棒
To be here and find you and see you well is wonderful.
我们也有机会叙叙旧
And we have a chance to catch up.
不了，谢谢
No. Thank you so much.
我的兄弟
My brother.
丹尼尔，我的姻亲
Daniel, my brother by marriage.
我们真是老朋友了，这么多往日时光
We're such old friends. So much time.
世事多变
Things go up, things go down,
但至少主总是与我们同在
but at least the Lord is always around.
我们历经了人生起伏，不是吗？
We've seen ups and downs, haven't we?
你现在混得不好了，伊莱？
Are things down for you right now, Eli?
没有
No. No.
不过我的确带来了悲伤的消息
But l do come with some sad news.
也许你还记得班迪先生？
Perhaps you remember Mr. Bandy?
班迪先生蒙主恩宠了
Mr. Bandy has passed on to the Lord.
他于99岁辞世，上帝保佑他
He lived to be 99 years old, God bless him.
班迪先生有个孙子，你见过他孙子威廉吗？
Mr. Bandy has a grandson.
Have you met his grandson, William?
威廉班迪是我们第三启示教堂
William Bandy is one of the finest members we have
最优秀的成员之一
at the Church of the Third Revelation.
他很想到好莱坞演电影
He's eager to come to Hollywood to be in movies.
他的面貌非常俊秀
He is very good-looking.
-而我认为他会成功 -那太好了
-And l do think he will have success.
-That's wonderful.
你要我跟他谈吗？
Would you like me to speak with him?
丹尼尔，我是在问你想不想
Daniel, l'm asking if you'd like to have business
跟第三启示教堂一起携手
with the Church of the Third Revelation
开发小班迪的土地？
in developing this lease on young Bandy's 1,000-acre tract.
我在提议让你钻探
l'm offering you to drill
小波士顿未开发土地的精华之一
on one of the great undeveloped fields of Little Boston.
-我很乐意跟你合作 -你愿意？
-l'd be happy to work with you. -You would?
是啊，当然，那太好了
Yes, yes, of course. That's wonderful.
不过这合作有个条件
But there is one condition for this work.
好的
All right.
我要你告诉我你是个假先知
l'd like you to tell me that you are a false prophet.
我要你告诉我你是，以前也是一个假先知
l'd like you to tell me that you are,
and have been a false prophet.
还有上帝是个迷信
And that God is a superstition.
那可是谎言
But that's a lie.
那是谎言，我说不出口
lt's a lie. l cannot say it.
-我们何时可以开始钻探？ -很快
-When can we begin to drill? -Very soon.
油井要多久才能量产？
How long will it take to bring in the well?
应该不用多久
lt shouldn't take long.
我想要十万签约金
l would like a $100,000 signing bonus,
加上你欠我的五千元本利
plus the five that is owed to me with interest.
那很公平
That's only fair.
我是假先知，上帝也是迷信
l am a false prophet, and God is a superstition.
如果你这么想，我就说
lf that's what you believe, then l will say it.
-真心诚意的说 -丹尼尔
-Say it like you mean it. -Daniel.
就像你讲道一样
Say it like it's your sermon.
别笑
Don't smile.
我是假先知
l am a false prophet.
-上帝是迷信 -你何不站起来
-God is a superstition. -Why don't you stand up?
把杯子放下
Put your glass down.
我是假先知
l am a false prophet.
-上帝是迷信 -伊莱，停
-God is a superstition. -Eli, stop.
想像这里是你的教堂，你的教徒满坑满谷
Just imagine this is your church here
and you have a full congregation, so...
我是假先知，上帝是迷信
l am a false prophet. God is a superstition.
再说一次
Say it again.
我是假先知，上帝是迷信
l am a false prophet. God is a superstition.
后面的听不见
They can't hear you at the back.
我是假先知，上帝是迷信
l am a false prophet. God is a superstition.
再说一次
Say it again.
我是假先知，上帝是迷信
l am a false prophet! God is a superstition!
再说一次
Say it again.
我是假先知，上帝是迷信
l am a false prophet! God is a superstition!
那里的地已经被钻探过了
Those areas have been drilled.
什么？
What?
那里的地，已经钻探过了
Those areas, they've been drilled.
-不，并没有 -有的
-No, they haven't. -Yes, it's...
那叫汲取
lt's called drainage, Eli.
我拥有附近的地，当然就能得到下面的东西
See, l own everything around it, so,
of course, l get what's underneath it.
不过那里没有钻油井
But there are no derricks there.
我说的是班迪的地，你明白吗？
This is the Bandy tract. Do you understand?
伊莱，你明白吗？
Do you understand, Eli?
不止是那样，你明白吗？
That's more to the point. Do you understand?
我喝了你的水，我每天都喝
l drink your water. l drink it up every day.
我喝了班迪那块地的羔羊宝血
l drink the blood of Lamb from Bandy's tract.
你可以坐下了
You can sit down again.
丹尼尔
Daniel.
求求你
Please.
-我很绝望 -我知道
-l am in desperate times. -l know.
-我需要朋友 -当然，你需要
-l need a friend. -Yes. Of course, you do.
我有罪
l've sinned.
我需要帮忙，我是罪人
l need help. l'm a sinner.
我让恶魔以我无法想像的方法掌握住我
l've let the devil grab hold of me
in ways l never imagined.
我满身是罪
l'm so full of sin.
上帝有时会挑战我们，不是吗？
The Lord sometimes challenges us, doesn't He, Eli?
-是的，他会 -是的，他会
-Yes, He does, Daniel. -Yes, He does.
是的，他会
Yes, He does!
他完全没有警告我最近的经济恐慌
He's completely failed to alert me
to the recent panic in our economy.
-而这一切... -亲爱的
-And this... -Oh, dear.
我一定要开发这块地，我一定要、一定要开发
l must have this, Daniel. l must, l must, l must have this.
我的投资都...
My investments have...
我不逼你，不过若我能抓住上帝帮助的手
Daniel, l won't bore you, but if l could
grab the Lord's hand for help l would,
他常行如此神迹
but He does these things all the time.
他现出了那些神迹，我们等待...
These mysteries that He presents, and while we wait...
我们等待他的指示
While we wait for His word!
因为你不是上帝的兄弟，伊莱
Because you're not the chosen brother, Eli.
上帝的兄弟是保罗
'Twas Paul who was chosen.
他告诉我地的事，你只是个笨蛋
He found me and told me
about your land. You're just a fool.
-你为什么要说保罗？ -我做了你兄弟做不到的事
-Why are you talking about Paul?
-l did what your brother couldn't.
-别对我说这个 -我让你破产还打了你
-Don't say this to me.
-l broke you and l beat you.
保罗先把你的事告诉了我
lt was Paul told me about you.
他才是先知，他才有脑袋，他早知道那里有什么
He's the prophet. He's the smart one.
He knew what was there
他找我去把地下的东西挖出来
and he found me to take it out of the ground.
知道最好笑的是什么吗？听着
Know what the funny thing is? Listen, listen.
我当面给了他一万元现金，就这样
l paid him $10,000 cash in hand. Just like that.
他现在拥有自己的公司，不错的小事业
He has his own company now. Prosperous little business.
三口井量产，每周五千元
Three wells producing, $5,000 a week.
别哀嚎了，你这个爱哭鬼。别胡闹了
Stop crying, you sniveling ass. Stop your nonsense.
- 你只是个胎盘，伊莱 - 不
-You're just the afterbirth, Eli.
-No.
是母体排出的秽物
That slithered out
on your mother's filth.
不
No.
他们应该把你放进罐子里当装饰品
They should've put you in a glass jar on the mantelpiece.
保罗在吸奶时，你在哪里？
Where were you when Paul was suckling at his mother's teat?
你在哪里？
Where were you?
谁在哺育你，可怜的伊莱？班迪家的母猪？
Who was nursing you, poor Eli?
One of Bandy's sows?
那块地已经干了，你无能为力
That land has been had.
Nothing you can do about it. lt's gone.
-你先看看这块地... -你输了
-lf you would just take this lease... -You lose.
干了
Drainage!
干了，伊莱，单纯的家伙
Drainage, Eli, you boy.
被吸干了，真对不起
Drained dry. l'm so sorry.
如果你有一杯奶昔
lf you have a milkshake
我也有一杯奶昔
and l have a milkshake,
我还有吸管，就在这，看到没？
and l have a straw, there it is.
That's the straw, you see?
看着
Watch it.
现在我的吸管跑过房间
Now my straw reaches across the room
开始吸你的奶昔
and starts to drink your milkshake.
我喝了你的奶昔
l drink your milkshake!
-我喝光了 -别欺负我，丹尼尔
-l drink it up! -Don't bully me, Daniel.
你真以为你的歌舞和迷信能够帮你？
Did you think your song and dance and
your superstition would help you, Eli?
我才是先知，我才是上帝选上的
l am the Third Revelation. l am who the Lord has chosen.
-丹尼尔！-因为我比你聪明
-Daniel! -Because l'm smarter than you!
我比你老
l'm older!
我是你的老朋友
l'm your old friend, Daniel!
-我不是假先知 -救救我!救救我!
-l'm not a false prophet... -Help me! Help me!
你这个爱哭鬼
...you sniveling boy!
我才是先知，我才是先知
l am the Third Revelation! l am the Third Revelation!
-我说过我会吃了你 -我们是一家人
-l told you l would eat you. -We're family!
-我说过我会吃光你 -我们是兄弟!我们是兄弟!
-l told you l would eat you up!
-We're brothers! We're brothers!
丹尼尔，原谅我，我求你
Daniel, please forgive me. l beg you.
就是这样，就是这样
That's it. That's it.
丹尼尔先生？
Mr. Daniel?
我完了
l'm finished.
黑金企业